<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.3//EN" "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.3/docbookx.dtd"  [ ]>

<chapter id="intro">
  <title>Introduction to the Meteor Framework</title>
  
  <para>The chapter is an introduction to how Meteor implements its <link linkend="design_goals">design goals</link>.
  To reiterate, the Meteor framework has four main design goals which were adopted 
  in order to meet its business goal of making it possible to profitably develop 
  system software for small businesses:
  <itemizedlist>
  	<listitem><para>Dynamic, modular system assembly.</para></listitem>
  	<listitem><para>Model-driven system functionality.</para></listitem>
  	<listitem><para>Unanticipated customation, or customization without hooks.</para></listitem>
  	<listitem><para>Provide the most common system functionality out-of-the-box.</para></listitem>
  </itemizedlist>
  </para>
  
  
  <section>
  	<title>Java</title>
  	<para>
  	Meteor uses Java as the underlying runtime platform. 
  	The Java community provides a wealth of open source libraries that Meteor reuses. 
  	In the future it is highly probable that Meteor will support the development 
  	of Meteor modules in other languages that run on the Java Virtual Machine 
  	but for now all Meteor modules are developed with Java.      
  	</para>
  </section>
  
  <section>
  	<title>Dynamic, modular system assembly: OSGi Bundles</title>
  	<para>
  	Meteor's first design goal is to make it possible to assemble a software 
  	system from modules.  Instead of defining its own concept of what a module is 
  	Meteor instead has adopted the <ulink url="http://www.osgi.org">OSGi Service Framework</ulink> 
  	as the standard for defining what a module is, how modules are deployed, 
  	installed, started, etc. Therefore, all Meteor functionality is package into OSGi 'bundles'. 
  	All Meteor-based systems run on top of an OSGi 'engine' that manages all bundles.
  	</para>
  	<para>
  	A central focus of the OSGi framework is the concept of 'services'.  Meteor is 
  	designed to integrate well with existing OSGi services by making it possible to 
  	automatically 'inject' standard OSGi services into Meteor-managed resources and 
  	to automatically export Meteor-managed services as OSGi services.  
  	</para>
  	<para>
  	The OSGi framework also defines many standard services, like a Logging service, a Remoting service, etc. 
  	Meteor takes advantage of available OSGi services whenever possible.
  	</para>
  	<para>
  	Meteor uses the open source <ulink url="http://felix.apache.org/site/index.html">Felix OSGi engine</ulink> as its OSGi engine, however Meteor 
  	should work with other OSGi implementatio such as <ulink url="http://www.eclipse.org/equinox/">Equinox</ulink> and <ulink url="http://concierge.sourceforge.net/">Concierge</ulink>. 
  	</para>
  </section>
  
  <section>
  	<title>Model-driven system functionality: RDF (Resource Description Format) metadata repository</title>
	  <section>
	  	<title>Why RDF?</title>
	  	<para>
	  	Meteor's second design goal is to provide a global metadata repository.
	  	A metadata repository enabled model-driven development and make it possible for a module to 
	  	provide an aspect of functionality for the entire system.  For instance, 
	  	when the repository contains a description of all objects that will be persistently 
	  	stored then a single module can provide persistent storage to a database for the 
	  	entire system based on the data in the repository.
	  	</para>
	  	<para>
	  	Meteor has adopted the <ulink url="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Resource_Description_Framework">Resource Description Format</ulink> (RDF) 
	  	for representing metadata. 
	  	RDF is a general method for conceptual description or modeling of information. 
	  	Meteor defines a Java API for accessing and manipulating RDF data. 
	  	Meteor all supports the <ulink url="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Turtle_(syntax)">Turtle RDF serialization format</ulink>.
	  	</para>
	  	<para>
	  	Meteor uses RDF mainly because RDF makes it easy to do one thing that's not easy to 
	  	do in other modeling methods: RDF makes it easy for one module to state 
	  	facts about data in another module. 
	  	For instance, suppose one module contain metadata that defines contact information for a person.  
	  	Then suppose that another module wants to add a twitter id to that contact information. 
	  	This is exactly the kind of thing that is easy to do with RDF but is quite difficult 
	  	to do with other methods.  This feature of RDF is exactly what is needed in order to 
	  	make it possible for modules to customize each other.
	  	</para>
	  </section>
	  
	  <section>
	  	<title>What data is available in the repository?</title>
	  	<para>
	  	</para> 
	  </section>
  </section>
   
  <section>
  	<title>Unanticipated Customization: Metadata-driven Generic functions, Decorators, Interceptors and Dependency Injection</title>
  	<para>
  	Some existing application development frameworks make it easier to customize 
  	software by adding what are called hooks, or extension points. 
  	Take for example an order management module that calculates sales commissions 
  	on orders and suppose that this module wants to allow other modules to be 
  	able to customize how commissions are calculated. 
  	In many other frameworks in order to make it possible for other modules to 
  	customize the calculation of sales commissions the order management module 
  	would be required to define an 'extension-point', or hook, that other modules 
  	could use to register additional calculation methods. 
  	The problems with this type of customization are:
  	<itemizedlist>
  		<listitem>
  			<para>
  			It requires significant extra effort on the part of the developer to 
  			create the hooks used for customization and extension
  			</para>
  		</listitem>
  		<listitem>
  			<para>
  			It limits reuse since hooks have to be created <emphasis>before</emphasis> 
  			a module can be customized. 
  			However, developers never anticipate all the ways in which other 
  			developers may want to customize a module and even if they do they 
  			often don't make the effort to create hooks until and unless they 
  			know someone else is going to use them.
  			</para>
  		</listitem>
  	</itemizedlist>
  	For these reasons it is better to support an extension and customization 
  	scheme that does not require hooks, a scheme that enables modules to directly 
  	'plug into' objects from other modules.
  	</para>
  	<section>
	  	<title>Generic functions</title>
	  	<para>
	  	In Meteor all available functionality is defined by Java 
	  	interfaces and Meteor gives all modules the ability to customize the behavior 
	  	of any method of any interface defined by any other module. 
	  	In Meteor all interface methods are implemented using a technique called <firstterm>generic functions</firstterm>.  	 
	  	A generic function is a Java interface method and an associated collection 
	  	of Java class methods each of which implements the interface method. 
	  	At runtime when the interface method is invoked a subset of the methods are 
	  	selected for execution (depending on the current runtime context) and arranged 
	  	in a stack for execution.  The first invoked method may 
	  	choose to return a result and complete the invocation or it may choose to pass 
	  	the invocation further down the stack to the next method.
	  	</para>
	  	<para>
	  	Generic functions are described in detail in later sections.
	  	</para>
  	</section
  	
  	<section>
  		<title>Guice in Meteor</title>
	  	<para> 
	  	Instead of inventing its own 
	  	method of enabling the ability to customize behavior Meteor uses another 
	  	framework called <ulink url="http://code.google.com/p/google-guice/">Guice</ulink> 
	  	to provide this functionality. 
	  	Guice is well-know as a 'dependency injection' library but 
	  	Guice also implements a capability know as 'interceptors', the ability to 
	  	intercept and customize a method invocation on an interface.  Metoer reuses 
	  	Guice to provide the ability to customize method invocations and also reuses 
	  	Guice's dependency injection capability. 
	  	However, using Guice directly to customize behavior can be quite tedious. 
	  	Another problem with using Guice directly is that it's impossible for 
	  	someone to get a complete picture of how the modules in a system customize 
	  	each other. Therefore Meteor introduces the ability for modules to simply 
	  	create 'decorator' and 'interceptor' classes that plug-into interface 
	  	implementations. 
	  	Meteor then automatically creates system metadata that describes how 
	  	decorator and interceptor classes should be assembled into interface 
	  	implementation.  Meteor also automatically configures Guice with the 
	  	appropriate interceptors.  Decorator and interceptor classes may then 
	  	use Guice annotation for dependency injection purposes.  Guice 
	  	annotations may be used to inject Meteor-managed objects as well as 
	  	OSGi services. 
	  	</para>
	 </section>
  	<section>
  		<title>Decorator and Interceptor classes</title>
	  	<para> 
	  	To make Guice easier to use in a modular system Meteor introduces the 
	  	ability for modules to simply create 'decorator' and 'interceptor' 
	  	classes that can be plugged-into interface implementations. 
	  	Meteor then automatically creates system metadata that describes how 
	  	decorator and interceptor classes should be assembled into interface 
	  	implementation.  Meteor also automatically configures Guice with the 
	  	appropriate interceptors.  Decorator and interceptor classes may then 
	  	use Guice annotation for dependency injection purposes.  Guice 
	  	annotations may be used to inject Meteor-managed objects as well as 
	  	OSGi services.  The details of Decorators and Interceptors are described 
	  	in <link linkend="decorators_and_interceptors">this section.</link>
	  	</para>
	  	<para> 
	  	Because Meteor creates metadata in the system metadata repository that 
	  	describes how decorators and interceptors are wired together it is 
	  	possible to create a module to provide a system 'view' that provides a 
	  	convenient view of the system for understanding how modules are wired 
	  	together. Currently Metoer comes with a simple utility that creates a 
	  	document to show what modules contribute functionaly to what interfaces.
	  	</para>
	 </section>
  </section>
  
  <section>
  	<title>Out of the Box Functionality</title>
	  <section>
	  	<title>Role-based Authorization</title>
	  	<para>
	  	</para> 
	  </section>
	  <section>
	  	<title>Persistent Storage</title>
	  	<para>
	  	</para> 
	  </section>
	  <section>
	  	<title>WebBench User Interface</title>
	  	<para>
	  	</para> 
	  </section>
  </section>

</chapter>